J. Mol. Biol. (1991) 217, 353-371 
Refined Crystal Structures of Subtilisin Novo in Complex with 
Wild-type and Two Mutant Eglins 
Comparison with Other Serine Proteinase Inhibitor Complexes 
D. W. Heinz’?, J. P. Priestlel, J. Rahuel’, K. S. Wilson2 and M. G. Griitterlt 
1 Pharmaceutical Division 
Ciba-Geigy Ltd 
4002 Base1 
Switzerland 
2European Molecular Biology Laboratory, c/o DES Y 
Notkestrasse 85 
2000 Hamburg 52 
West Germany 
(Received 16 July 1990; accepted 20 September 1990) 
The crystal structures of the complexes formed between subtilisin Novo and three 
inhibitors, eglin c, Arg45-eglin c and Lys53-eglin c have been determined using molecular 
replacement and difference Fourier techniques and refined at 2.4 A, 2.1 A and 2.4 A 
resolution, respectively. 
The mutants Arg45-eglin c and Lys53-eglin c were constructed by site-directed 
mutagenesis in order to investigate the inhibitory specificity and stability of eglin c. 
Arg45-eglin became a potent trypsin inhibitor, in contrast to native eglin, which is an 
elastase inhibitor. This specificity change was rationalized by comparing the structures of 
Arg45-eglin and basic pancreatic trypsin inhibitor and their interactions with trypsin. The 
residue Arg53, which participates in a complex network of hydrogen bonds formed between 
the core and the binding loop of eglin c, was replaced with the shorter basic amino acid 
lysine in the mutant Lys53-eglin. Two hydrogen bonds with Thr44, located in the binding 
loop, can no longer be formed but are partially restored by a water molecule bound in the 
vicinity of Lys53. 
Eglin c in complexes with both subtilisin Novo and subtilisin Carlsberg was crystallized in 
two different space groups. Comparison of the complexes showed a rigid body rotation for 
the eglin c core of 11.5” with respect to the enzyme, probably caused by different 
intermolecular contacts in both crystal forms. 
1. Introduction 
Serine proteinases are physiologically important 
proteolytic enzymes, as demonstrated by the pre- 
sence of numerous different protein inhibitors that 
have evolved to control their activity. A general 
kinetic mechanism for the inhibition, the so-called 
standard mechanism, which is valid for most serine 
proteinase inhibitors has been postulated 
(Laskowski & Kato, 1980). The inhibitor binds with 
its reactive site binding loop to the active site of the 
t Present address: Institute of Molecular Biology and 
Department of Physics, University of Oregon, Eugene, 
OR 97493, U.S.A. 
$ Author to whom all correspondence should be 
addressed. enzyme by mimicking a substrate. The scissile 
peptide bond located in the binding loop, however, 
is cleaved extremely slowly, if at all, due to the rigid 
conformation of the binding loop, which tightly 
binds to the enzyme. The loop is held in its confor- 
mation by either mainly covalent interactions with 
the rest of the inhibitor molecule formed by disul- 
fide bridges, as in basic pancreatic trypsin inhibitor 
(BPTQ: Deisenhofer & Steigemann, 1974), or by 
$ Abbreviations used: BPTI, basic pancreatic trypsin 
inhibitor; SSI, Streptomyces subtilisin inhibitor; CI, 
chymotrypsin inhibitor; WTNOVO, complex wild-type 
eglin/subtilisin Novo; R45NOV0, complex 
Arg45_eglin/subtilisin Novo; K53NOV0, complex 
Lys53_eglin/subtilisin Novo; WTCARL, complex wild- 
type eglin/subtilisin Carlsberg; r.m.s., root-mean-square. 
0022-2836/91/020353-19 $03.00/O 353 
0 1991 Academic Press Limited 354 D. W. Heinz et al. 
Figure 1. Plot of the main-chain atoms of eglin (open bonds). The side-chains of Leu45 (Pl) and amino acids involved 
in binding loop stabilization (Thr44, Asp46, Arg51, Ag53 and Gly70) are also shown (filled bonds). 
non-covalent interactions, as found in the inhibitors 
of the potato I inhibitor family (McPhalen & James, 
1988). 
Eglin c, isolated from the leech Hirudo medicina- 
lis, strongly inhibits a-chymotrypsin, chymase, 
subtilisin and the neutrophilic proteinases elastase 
and cathepsin G (Seemiiller et al., 1980). It has 
attracted particular attention as a possible thera- 
peutic agent against various pathogenic processes, 
in which elastase and cathepsin play a major role, 
such as pulmonary emphysema and shock (Schnebli 
& Braun, 1986). Eglin c lacks the sulfur-containing 
amino acids cysteine and methionine and shows a 
remarkably high resistance to denaturation by heat 
and acid (Seemiiller et al., 1980). The gene coding for 
eglin c has been synthesized by enzymatic ligation 
of chemically synthesized DNA fragments and 
expressed in Escherichia co&i (Rink et cd., 1984). 
Recombinant eglin c (referred to in the following 
simply as eglin) was shown to have similar physico- 
chemical and identical biological properties as the 
native protein isolated from the leech (Raschdorf et 
al., 1986). Eglin belongs to the potato I inhibitor 
family (Laskowski & Kato, 1980), which also 
includes two yeast proteinase B inhibitors (Maier et 
al., 1979), the barley seed inhibitors U-1 and CI-2 
(Svendsen et al., 1982; Jonassen & Svendsen, 1982) 
and the potato I inhibitor (Richardson & Cossins, 
1974). A common feature of these inhibitors is the 
absence of disulfide bridges. 
The crystal structure of the complex formed 
between eglin and subtilisin Carlsberg has been 
elucidated by X-ray structure analysis (McPhalen et 
al., 1985o; Bode et al., 1986~) and refined at high 
resolution. Eglin consists of a hydrophobic core and 
an exposed proteinase binding loop (residues 40 to 
48: Fig. 1). The hydrophobic core contains a twisted 
four-stranded /I-sheet and a short a-helix (residues 
18 to 25). The binding loop with the scissile bond between residues Leu45 (Pl)? and Asp46 (Pl’), is 
held in its conformation by electrostatic and hydro- 
gen bond interactions. Residues Thr44 and Asp46, 
both located in the binding loop, interact with 
Arg51 and Arg53 on the core’s surface, with the 
C-terminal Gly70 and, in addition, with several 
solvent molecules. The stabilization of the confor- 
mation by exclusively non-covalent interactions is 
unique and has so far been found only in the struc- 
turally homologous inhibitor CI-2 from barley seeds 
(McPhalen et al., 19855). 
In order to focus on the roles of individual amino 
acids in determining the inhibitory specificity and in 
stabilizing the conformation of the binding loop, a 
series of eglin mutants has been constructed by site- 
directed mutagenesis. A change in specificity of 
eglin from an elastase inhibitor to a trypsin inhibi- 
tor was attempted by replacing Leu45 in position 
Pl by Arg. The putative important role of Arg53 in 
the hydrogen bonding network between the binding 
loop and the core of eglin was investigated by the 
replacement of Arg53 with the shorter basic amino 
acid lysine. 
Subtilisins are bacterial serine proteinases with a 
molecular mass of about 28 kDa and a preferential 
specificity for large amino acids in the Pl position of 
substrates (or inhibitors). Subtilisin Carlsberg (from 
Badus subti&s) and subtilisin Novo (or BPN’) (from 
Bacillus amykdiqwfaciens) (classification according 
to Welker & Campbell (1967)) have very similar 
tertiary structures, but their primary structures 
differ in 82 amino acids (out of 275) and an insertion 
t Nomenclature of Schechter & Berger (1967). Amino 
acids of inhibitors or substrates are named Pl, P2, P3 
etc. toward the N terminus and Pl’, P2’, P3’ etc. toward 
the C terminus from the scissile peptide bond. The 
complementary binding subsites of the enzyme are 
named Sl, S2 etc., and Sl’, 52’ etc. Subtilisin-Eglin Crystal Structure 355 
of one amino acid (Thr55 in subtilisin Novo) 
(McPhalen t James, 1988). The crystal structure of 
subtilisin Novo has been determined in the native 
form (Wright et al., 1969; Drenth et al., 1972) and in 
complex with both Streptmnyces subtilisin inhibitor 
(SSI: Hirono et al., 1934) and chymotrypsin 
inhibitor 2 from barley seeds ((X-2: McPhalen et al., 
1985b). The structure of the latter complex has been 
completely refined at 2.1 A resolution 
(1 A = 01 nm). No crystal structure has been 
reported for the complex formed between eglin and 
subtilisin Novo. 
Here, we describe the elucidation and analysis of 
the crystal structures of wild-type eglin and the 
mutants Arg45-eglin and Lys53-eglin in complex 
with subtilisin Novo. The structures of the eglin 
complexes with both subtilisins Novo and Carlsberg 
are compared. The inhibitory properties of 
Arg45-eglin are explained by comparing its struc- 
ture with that of BPTI. The contribution of Arg53 
to the binding loop stabilization is discussed on the 
basis of the crystal structures of both wild-type and 
Ly$&eglin, and correlated with kinetic data. The 
complexes of subtilisin Novo with wild-type eglin, 
Arg45-eglin and Lys53-eglin will be referred to as 
WTNOVO, R45NOVO and K53NOV0, respect- 
ively, and the complex of subtilisin Carlsberg with 
wild-type eglin as WTCARL. 
2. Materials and Methods 
(a) Site-directed mutagenesis and putifiation 
Oligonucleotide-directed mutagenesis was performed 
according to the primer extension method of Zoller & 
Smith (1983). Experimental details will be published else- 
where. Mutant eglin genes were expressed in E. coli JA221 
(Clarke & Carbon, 1978) under control of the trp 
promoter. Cell walls were mechanically lysed using a 
dyno-mill. Eglin mutants were purified using an acid 
extraction followed by gel filtration (Sephadex G50 SF; 
Pharmacia, Uppsala, Sweden) and reversed phase, high- 
pressure liquid chromatography. 
(b) Kinetic studies 
The determination of kinetic constants describing the 
inhibition of the serine proteinases human leukocyte elas- 
tase, subtilisin and bovine trypsin by eglin mutants was 
performed by a method similar to that described by 
Braun et aZ. (1987). All enzymes were active site-titrated. 
The substrates Bz-Arg-p-nitroanilide (-pNA) (Bachem, 
Bubendorf, Switzerland) and methoxy-succinyl-Arg-Pro- 
Tyr-pNA (KabiVitrum, Stockholm, Sweden) were used 
for the assays of trypsin and subtilisin, respectively. 
Experimental details will be published elsewhere. 
Preliminary inhibition experiments with human thrombin 
and porcine kallikrein were undertaken using o-Phe-Pip- 
Arg-pNA and Chromozym GK (Boehringer-Mannheim, 
Germany), respectively. 
(c) Crystallization 
Lyophilized subtilisin (from B. subtilis; 5 units/mg) was 
purchased from Boehringer-Mannheim, Germany. Eglin 
(mutants) and subtilisin were stoichiometrically mixed at a total protein concentration of 60 mg/ml in 
91 M-potassium phosphate buffer (pH 6) to obtain 
complexes in the ratios 1 : 1 to l-5 : 1 (w/w). Crystallization 
was performed using the hanging-drop vapor diffusion 
method (Davies & Segal, 1971). In a typical experiment, 
5 ~1 of protein solution and 5 ~1 of a reservoir solution 
containing 10 to 15% (w/v) polyethylene glycol 
(PEG 4000) in @l M-potassium phosphate buffer (pH a), 
were mixed on a siliconized cover slip, and then sealed 
with Vaseline over a small well containing 500 ~1 of 
reservoir solution. 
(d) Data collection and processing 
X-ray intensity data from crystals of R45NOVO were 
collected using 2 different methods and instruments. 
A complete dataset to 45 A resolution using a single 
crystal was collected on a CAD4F 4-circle diffractometer 
(Enraf Nonius, Delft, The Netherlands) operated at 
40 kV/40 mA and controlled by a VAX 1 l/730 computer. 
The crystal was kept at 4°C. At the termination of data 
collection, 15% intensity decay had occurred. Anisotropic 
crystal absorption (North et al., 1968) and corrections for 
Lorentz and polarization effects were performed during 
data reduction. Baysian statistics were applied to deter- 
mine the best intensity estimate of very weak reflections 
(French & Wilson, 1978). 
Data were collected to higher resolution using synchro- 
tron radiation (Deutsches Elektronen Synchrotron 
(DESY) at the EMBL outstation, Hamburg, Germany). 
The X-ray source was the beam line Xl 1, which uses 
X-rays generated by the positron current. The wave- 
*length of the beam was set to 1.464 A. Data were collected 
from 4 randomly oriented crystals (sizes -02 mm x 
92 mm x 93 mm) on CEA film with 2 films/pack using an 
Arndt-Wonacott oscillation camera. A series of 20 photo- 
graphs with an oscillation range of 1.5” and an exposure 
time of 60 s/film pack was taken from each crystal, with a 
crystal to film distance of 57 mm. The reflections on the 
films were digitized on an Optronies P-1000 Photoscan 
System rotating drum film scanning microdensitometer 
with a 50 pm raster and an absorbance scale of 3.0. 
The orientation of the crystals was determined using an 
autoindexing program developed by Kabsch (1988) baaed 
on a list of observed reflection positions. The misset angles 
in all 3 directions were determined for the first, the last 
and a middle B film, then averaged. The oscillation films 
were processed using a version of the Cambridge oscil- 
lation program system (Nyborg & Wonacott, 1977), which 
uses the profile analysis algorithm of Rossmann (1979) as 
modified by Wilson et al. (1983). Oblique-incidence film 
absorption correction for more widely scattered X-rays 
was performed and scale factors between A and B films 
were calculated and intensity corrections (Lorentz-polari- 
zation and transmission correction) applied. Data were 
processed to a resolution of 2.1 A. Typically, 200 reflec- 
tions on the A films and 30 reflections on the B films were 
overexposed. The reliability indices Raea,=? and Rsym were 
usually between 904 and 905: 74,306 measurements 
merged to 21,538 unique reflections after film to film 
t The reliability index is defined as R = Gil <Ii > 
-Iii/&Ii, and <Ii> is the average of Ii over all its 
symmetry equivalents. RsEale is determined between A 
and B films, &r,,, and Rmcrgc describe the agreement of 
symmetry-related reflections on one film or on different 
films, respectively. 356 D. W. Heinz et al. 
scaling using the algorithm of Fox & Holmes (1966). The 
final Rmcrce value of 4 crystals with data to 2.1 A resolu- 
tion was 9136. Baysian statistics were used to obtain the 
best estimate of the true reflection intensity for weakly 
and negatively measured reflections (French & Wilson, 
1978). 
Data for crystals of WTNOVO and K53NOVO were 
collected on a FAST area detector (Enraf Nonius, Delft, 
The Netherlands). Graphite monochromated CuKa radia- 
tion was produced by an Enraf Nonius FR571 rotating 
anode generator operated at 40 kV/70 mA with an 
apparent focal spot of 93 mm x 63 mm. The capillary was 
mounted on a 4-circle kappa goniostat. Rotations around 
the o-axis were performed in steps of @IO/frame with an 
exposure time of 60 to 120 s/frame. The 28 angle for the 
detector was 15” for data collection to 24 A resolution 
with a crystal to detector distance of 50 mm. The orien- 
tation of the crystals, data collection and on-line data 
evaluation were done using the program MADNES 
(Messerschmidt & Pflugrath, 1987). The measured inten- 
sity data were profile-fitted and scaled together using the 
program PROCOR (developed by W. Kabsch, EMBL 
Heidelberg). The final R,,,crsc values of FAST-data to 2.4 A 
resolution were 9083 for WTNOVO (using 
- 6097 for K53NOVO (using 3 crystals). 1 crystal) and 
(e) Structure determination 
The structure of R45NOVO was solved by molecular 
replacement using diffractometer data between 8 A and 
45 A. The refined structure of WTCARL at 1.2 A resolu- 
tion (Bode et al., 1986a) was used as the trial structure. 
This structure was placed into a Pl cell with arbitrary 
chosen cell constants (a=b=c= 196 A; a=/I=y=9@‘). 
Structure factors were calculated within the resolution 
range 15 to 4.5 A. Two different rotation function 
programs (ALMN and POLARRFN, program package 
CCP4) were used to determine whether a unique solution 
for the orientation of the trial structure in the P3,(,,21 
cell could be found. The trial structure (in space group 
Pl) was first rotated in 2.5” steps in tl (0” <CL < 120”) and 
y (0” <y<369”) and in 10” steps in /l (O”<fi<96”) using 
the ALMN function to obtain a coarse solution. The 
angles a, B and y are the Eulerian rotation angles around 
z, y and z, respectively. The next ALMN function was 
then run in steps of 2.5” for /l in the vicinity of the coarse 
solution. POLARRFN was run to confirm the resulting 
rotation angles. 
For the translation function, the program TFSGEN 
(developed by I. Tickle, Birkbeck College, London, incor- 
porated into the CCP4 package) was used. The trial 
structure was placed in the correct orientation into both 
the p3, 21 and P3,21 unit cells. The translation function 
7’2 (incorporated in TFSGEN) developed by Crowther & 
Blow (1967) was used to find the position of the unknown 
structure in both possible space groups. Data between 10 
and 45 A were included. The crystal structures of 
WTNOVO and K53NOVO were solved by difference 
Fourier techniques (F0-FR45r ~a.+~: Stryer et al., 1964), 
where c(sd5 are the phases and #‘RF5 the structure factors 
calculated from the refined structure of R45NOVO 
(R=0.194). For both structures, data collected to 2.4 A 
resolution using an area detector were used. The struc- 
tures were initially inspected by calculating a 
Sim-weighted (Sim, 1966) difference electron density map 
(Fo-Frus; L+~), after omitting the atoms of the side- 
chains of Arg45 and Arg53. The new side-chains Leu45 
and Lys53 were built into the positive density of the 
difference Fourier map. (f) Model improvement 
The model structure obtained from molecular replace- 
ment at 45 A resolution was used as the starting point for 
the refinement of the R45NOVO structure. First, the 
structure was refined by rigid body refinement using the 
program CORELS (Sussman et al., 1977) against 
diffractometer data between 10 and 8 A resolution. 
Subtilisin was treated as if it were built up from four rigid 
parts of approximately 70 amino acid residues each, 
whereas Arg45-eglin was refined as a single piece. 
Individual atom refinement using the program PROLSQ 
(Hendrickson t Konnert, 1980) was done using all synch- 
rotron data under stepwise inclusion of data to a resolu- 
tion of 21 A. No bulk water correction was performed. 
After reaching a local minimum, difference Fourier maps 
were inspected on the picture system E&S PS399 using 
the program FRODO (Jones, 1978) to perform manual 
corrections and rebuilds. The use of F,,- Fc Fourier maps, 
in which the poorly defined atoms are omitted from the F, 
calculation, was found to be a sensitive technique for 
examining weak parts of the structure. A maximum of 
15% of the total number of atoms were omitted at a time. 
Tightly bound solvent molecules were introduced directly 
into the electron density or after calculating a difference 
Fourier map (F,, - F,) and looking for positive density at a 
distance of about 3 A to appropriate protein atoms. 
The structures of K53NOVO and WTNOVO were 
refined in a similar way. Structure factors and phases 
were calculated from the co-ordinates of the refined struc- 
ture of R45NOVO after replacement of the respective 
mutated amino acid and the rejection of solvent molecules 
in the proximity of the site of mutation with B>60 A2. 
Data between 50 and 2.4 A were used throughout. After 5 
to 8 cycles, new solvent molecules, located by difference 
Fourier maps, were introduced and manual corrections 
were carried out. 
3. Results 
(a) Inhibition kinetics 
Kinetic constants for wild-type eglin, Arg45-eglin 
and Lys53-eglin for the inhibition of human leuko- 
cyte elastase, bovine trypsin and subtilisin Novo are 
listed in Table 1. The single point mutation 
Leu45+Arg in position Pl changes eglin from an 
elastase inhibitor to a trypsin inhibitor. Lys53-eglin 
was a 106fold weaker elastase-inhibitor compared 
to wild-type eglin and a substrate of typsin. Both 
mutants are slightly weaker subtilisin inhibitors 
(increase of k,,) compared to wild-type eglin. 
Despite the presence of a basic amino acid in posi- 
tion Pl, Arg45-eglin showed no inhibition of human 
thrombin or porcine pancreatic kallikrein. 
(b) Crystallizatioin 
Trigonal pyramidal crystals of WTNOVO, 
R45NOVO and K53NOV0, reaching a size of about 
03 mm x 0.3 mm x 0.5 mm, were grown within three 
weeks at 20°C. The isomorphous crystals belong to 
the trrgonal space group P3,0, 21 and have unit cell 
edges of a=b=849A and c=891 A. There is one 
complex (36,006 daltons) per asymmetric unit, 
corresponding to V, = 2.5 A3/dalton (Matthews, 
1968). The presence of the appropriate subtilisin- Subtilisin-Eglin Crystal Structure 
Table 1 
Kinetic constants describing the interactions of human leukocyte elastase, bovine 
trypsin and subtilisin Novo with wild-type and mutant eglins 
Inhibitor Ki (M) (elastase) Ki (M) (trypsin) K, (M) (subtilisin) 
Wild-type eglin 
Arg45-eglin 
LydS-eglin 2.0 x lo-” 
Weak inhibition 
1.1 x 1o-9 Weak inhibition 
2.5 x lo-” 
Weak inhibition 3.2 x lo-” 
54 x lo-” 
1.1 x 10-10 
Weak inhibition implies that no Ki value can be measured using this method. 
eglin (mutant) complex in the crystals was 
confirmed by gel electrophoresis and isoelectric 
focusing. 
Crystals of the complex between eglin (mutants) 
and subtilisin from B. subtilis (Boehringer; expira- 
tion date (ED) 10/87) crystallized in the trigonal 
space group P3,,,, 21, whereas the complex between 
wild-type eglin and the same subtilisin (Boehringer; 
ED 12/86) crystallized in the triclinic space group 
Pl (Griitter et al., 1985) as was found for subtilisin 
Carlsberg in other laboratories (Bode et al., 1986a, 
McPhalen et al., 1985a). It was found during struc- 
ture refinement that subtilisin Novo instead of the 
expected subtilisin Carlsberg was present in the 
trigonal crystals. By comparing the expiration dates 
of the different subtilisin batches from Boehringer, 
we found that the content had been changed from 
subtilisin Carlsberg to subtilisin Novo during 1986 
without proper notification. Problems with commer- 
cially available subtilisins seem to be quite common. 
For example, subtilisin Novo, purchased from Serva 
(Heidelberg, Germany), contained subtilisin 
Carlsberg. This was found during refinement of the 
structure of WTCARL (Bode et al., 1986a). Similar 
cases of “subtilisin-confusion” have been reviewed 
by Russell & Fersht (1986). 
Several attempts were made to co-crystallize the 
complex of trypsin with its inhibitor Arg45-eglin. 
Promising, large crystals of this complex were 
obtained from PEG 4000 after one week. 
Unfortunately, the space group for these crystals 
could not be determined due to disorder in the 
diffraction pattern. Crystals of the complex between 
Arg45-eglin and trypsin obtained from ammonium 
sulfate (space group R2) diffracted weakly and were 
not suitable for X-ray structure analysis. 
(c) Structure determination 
The structure of R45NOVO was solved by 
molecular replacement using the high-resolution 
structure of the complex eglinsubtilisin Carlsberg 
(Bode et al., 1986a) as a trial model. The highest 
peak in the rotation map using the program ALMN 
at u = 57.5”, /3 = 57.5” and y = 185” had a height of 7.3 
standard deviations (6) above the mean, while the 
next highest peak was less than 40 above the mean. 
Very similar rotation angles were obtained with 
POLARRFN (a = 57.5”, B = 60*3”, y = 183.5”; highest 
peak 100; next highest peak 52.9). The translation function program TFSGEN was run for both 
possible space groups P31 21 and P3,21. The high- 
est peak (in arbitrary units) in the translation map 
(containing translation vectors t) for P3,21 (f., = 
167&l; 16~; next highest peak t=lOOO) was much 
higher than that for P32 21 (&,,= 10456; 570; next 
highest peak t= 1007), implying that the space 
group P3,21 was correct. Support for the correct- 
ness of the solution was obtained through an inter- 
molecular contact search in space group P31 21. 
Only three contacts between symmetry-equivalent 
complexes were less than 2 A. The initial overall 
R-factor (R = Xl1F.J - (FJ/XIF,I) before starting 
refinement was 0.44 in the resolution range of 45 to 
10 A. 
The structures of K53NOVO and WTNOVO, 
which crystallized isomorphously to R45NOV0, 
were solved by difference Fourier techniques. The 
highest positive density (9c above the mean) in the 
initial difference Fourier omit map was found at the 
site of amino acid changes. The initial R-factors 
between refined R45NOVO and K53NOVO and 
WTNOVO before refinement were 0.221 and 0.219, 
respectively. 
(d) Model improvement 
The model of R45NOVO was refined as rigid 
bodies using the program CORELS (Sussman et al., 
1977) resulting in an R-factor improvement from 
0442 to @420. When the trial structure was 
compared with the structure of R45NOVO it was 
obvious that the conformation of subtilisin was 
nearly the same, whereas the core of Arg45-eglin 
relative to subtilisin had undergone a rigid body 
rotation. The course of restrained least-squares 
refinement using the program PROLSQ 
(Hendrickson & Konnert, 1980) is shown in 
Figure 2: 97 cycles of refinement interrupted by 
seven sessions of manual rebuilding reduced the 
R-factor to @186. After cycle 42 (R=@259), indi- 
vidual isotropic temperature factors were refined. 
Refinement could not improve the structure to an 
R-factor better than 0224. A number of side-chains 
of subtilisin did not fit the electron density. At this 
point it was becoming clear that subtilisin Novo 
instead of the expected subtilisin Carlsberg was 
present in the crystals. After the subtilisin Novo 
sequence was built into the electron density, the 358 D. W. Heinz et al. 
0 IO 20 30 40 50 60 70 so 90 loo 
Number of refinement cycles 
Figure 2. The course of the crystallographic R-factor 
during refinement of R45NOV0, showing the R-factor as 
a function of refinement cycle. A, data to 3.0 8; B, data to 
26 A; C, data to 2.1 A; D, inclusion of 120 solvent 
molecules; E, refinement of individual isotropic 
temperature factors; F, replacement of 82 amino acids 
(subtilisin Carlsberg+Novo); G, final R-factor=@186 
after cycle 97. R-factor initially increased to 6272 and finally 
reached R = 0.186 (Table 2). 
In the refinement of K53NOVO and WTNOVO, 
all data between 5 and 2.4 d were included, and 
individual isotropic temperature refinement was 
performed. Refinement was terminated in the case 
of K53NOVO after 42 cycles (R = 0159) and for 
WTNOVO after 20 cycles (R=0169: Table 2). 
(e) Accuracy of the model 
The Ramachandran plot (Ramakrishnan & 
Ramachandran, 1965) for the complex of 
R45NOVO afer refinement (R = 6186 at 21 A reso- 
lution) is shown in Figure 3. Large clusters of 
residues are found at b-strand ( - 150” < 4 < - 50”; 
90”<~<180”) and right-handed E-helix 
(-lsoo<C#J< -50”; - 70” < t) < -40”) regions. Most 
of the residues outside the allowed region are 
glycine. Most of the non-glycine residues outside 
these regions are located close to the region charac- 
Table 2 
Summary of the rejinements of the structures of R45NOV0, K53NO VO and 
WTNOVO 
R45NOVO K53NOVO WTNOVO 
No. of cycles 97 42 20 
R-factor (%) l&+6 159 16.9 
Resolution range (A) 50-2.1 5G2.4 50-2.4 
No. of reflections 2cuE34 11195 11255 
No. of protein atoms 2474 2460 2462 
No. of solvent atoms 316 265 245 
No. of stereochemical restraints 12370 12295 12426 
Mean co-ordinate shift in final cycle 0667 0.038 904 
Mean B-factor shift in final cycle 914 1.14 676 
r.m.s. deviations from ideal values?: 
Distance restraints (A) 
Bond distance 
Angle distance 
Planar 14 distance 
Plane restraints (A) 
Chiral center restraints (As) 
Conformational torsion angle 
restraints (deg.) 
Planar angles (0) 
Staggered angles (e.g. xi) 
Orthonormsl angles (e.g. xz for aromatics) 
Non-bonded contact restraints (A) 
Single-torsion contact 
Multiple-torsion contact 
Possible intramolecular H-bond 
Possible intermolecular H-bond 
Isotropic thermal factor restraints (A’) 
Main-chain bonded atoms 
Main-chain non-bonded atoms 
Side-chain bonded atoms 
Side-chain non-bonded atoms 0.014 
0053 
0.058 
0.012 
0.166 
2.3 1.9 1.9 PO) 
20.2 21.8 21.8 (150) 
357 390 36.2 (20.0) 
0.21 0.22 921 (9.5) 
0.28 930 0.29 (6.5) 
031 630 0.31 (95) 
0.42 0.37 937 (9.5) 
4.05 4.19 407 (46) 
553 623 5.87 W’) 
10.4 127 11.3 (10.0) 
11.9 152 136 (150) 0.011 
0.048 
0.047 
0011 
0.151 0012 
0647 
0.049 
0.010 
0.155 (602) 
(0.04) 
(0.05) 
(902) 
(915) 
t The values of 6, in parentheses, are the input estimated standard deviations that determine the 
relative weights of the corresponding restraints (Hendrickson & Konnert, 1989). S&?&in-Eglin Crystal Structure 359 
-‘20t:..: l..:.‘i’. “....,. =i / / f”“K, 
-IS0 -120 -60 0 60 120 160 
+ (deg.) 
Figure 3. The 4/$-plot of R45NOVO. Non-glycine 
residues are indicated by diamonds and glycine residues 
by crosses. The continuous lines define areaa of allowed 
conformations with r(N-C”-C) = 1 lo”, the broken lines of 
conformations with t = 115” and relaxed van der Waals’ 
restraints. 
teristic for left-handed a-helices (30 < I$ < 60”; 
30” < + < 90”). The only non-glycine residues 
located far outside the allowed regions were Asn25 
(4=68”; $= -11”) and Ser63 (4=121”; $= -23”) 
in subtilisin Novo. Both residues are located in 
short turns connecting secondary structure 
elements. Ser63, which is located just before helix C, 
is glycine in subtilisin Carlsberg, Overall, the plots 
do not indicate any serious errors in the final model. 
This was true also for the models of K53NOVO and 
WTNOVO (plots not shown). 
An estimation of the accuracy of the model of 
R45NOVO could be obtained from the a,-plot 
(Read, 1986) shown in Figure 4. The overall root- 
mean-square co-ordinate error for R45NOVO is 
929 11, as estimated from the slope of the a,-plot 
after omitting the first two and the last three points. 
This value is slightly higher than one would expect 
I I I I . 
-% O-01 002 O-03 004 0.05 
sit? e/ AZ (h-9 
Figure 4. A a,-plot for data recorded from crystals of 
R45NOVO to 2.1 A resolution. The line, fitted by a least- 
squares procedure by leaving out the 1st 3 and the last 3 
points, corresponds to an r.m.s. co-ordinate error of 
0.29 A. c I Arg45- 
60 Eglin Subtilisin Novo 
50 
40 
30 
20 
IO 
%204060l 40 00 I20 160 200 ‘240 27 
Residue number 
Figure 5. A plot representing the main-chain 
temperature factors B (A’), averaged over N, C”, C and 0, 
w a function of residue number for Arg45-eglin and 
subtilisin Novo. Residues belonging to the catalytic triad 
in subtilisin are indicated, the position of the scissile bond 
in Arg45-eglin is labeled with a star. The average B-value 
is 2&l A2 for subtilisin Novo and 341 A2 for Arg-45-eglin. 
for a refined structure at that resolution, e.g. for the 
structure of the complex CI-2/eubtilisin Novo, 
which was refined at the same resolution 
(R=154%), a co-ordinate error of 621 A was 
estimated (McPhalen & James, 1988). 
The average B-value in the final model for the 
entire complex including 316 solvent molecules was 
31.1 A2, 28.1 A2 for subtilisin alone and 34.1 A2 for 
Arg45eglin (Fig. 5). The solvent molecules had an 
average B-value of 446 A2, water molecules with 
B> 80 A2 having been rejected. The highest 
B-values in the complex are found for exposed side- 
chains on the surface, whereas the lowest B-values 
are observed around the catalytic triad of subtilisin 
and for the binding loop of Ar 45-eglin. The mean 
B-value for Arg45-eglin (341 A B 
for subtilisin (28.1 A2), ) is higher than that 
indicating a greater flexi- 
bility of the inhibitor in the crystals, due to fewer 
crystal contacts. This was observed also in the case 
of the refined structure of WTCARL at 1.2 A resolu- 
tion (Bode et al., 1987), where the mean B-value was 
10 A2 for subtilisin and 16 A2 for eglin. 
(f) Analysis of the refined structures 
In R45NOV0, the overall folding of the subtilisin 
Novo as well as the orientation of most of the side- 
chains correspond to that found in the 
CI-B/subtilisin Novo complex (McPhalen & James, 
1988). Only side-chains at the surface, involved in 
close contacts with symmetry-equivalent complexes 
in the crystal, show differences in their orientation 
(e.g. Ser53, Thr158, Arg186 and Ser188). Both 
calcium-binding sites that were reported for subti- 
lisin Novo and Carlsberg, were also found with an 
identical ion co-ordination geometry. The occu- 
pancy of both ions is similar, as indicated by nearly 
identical temperature factors (B = 30 ii’). Since no 
calcium was added to the crystallization solution, 
both ions probably co-purified with the enzyme. 
The (Y-atoms of subtilisin Novo in R45NOVO 
were superimposed with the equivalent atoms of the 360 D. W. Heinz et al. 
0 50 ml 150 200 250 275 
Residue number 
Figure 6. A plot showing the differences (in A) of 
C”-positions of subtilisin Novo in R45NOVO and co- 
crystallized with CI-2 (McPhalen et al., 198%) after 
superposition using a least-squares procedure (r.m.s. 
deviation =031 A). The largest differences are found for 
Alal (A), Ser53 (B), Tyr104 (C), Gly131 (D) and Serl61 
(EL 
complex CI-2/subtilisin Novo (McPhalen et al., 
19853: and see Fig. 6). The r.m.s. deviation for the 
C” atoms was 631 A, which is close to the mean 
co-ordinate error of 629 A estimated from the 
o,-plot (Read, 1986). Deviations larger than 0.7 A 
were found in only five regions. The N terminus 
Alal, which is flexible, shows a slightly different 
orientation. Ser53 and Serl61 are located in highly 
flexible exterior loops that are not well defined in 
the electron density. Tyr104 is located in the S4 
hydrophobic pocket. Its orientation is influenced by 
the shape of the P4 residue (Pro42 in eglin and Ile56 
in CI-2: Fig. 7). The flexible residue Tyr104 in subti- 
lisin is able to fit to different hydrophobic P4 
residues. Gly131 is located in a large exterior loop in 
the vicinity of Tyr104. The position of the catalytic 
triad (Asp32, His64 and Ser221) is essentially 
identical (deviations less than 0.1 A). 
The superposition of C” atoms of subtilisin Novo 
in R45NOVO and subtilisin Carlsberg in WTCARL 
(Bode et al., 1986a: Fig. 8), showed an r.m.s. devia- 
tion of 072 A (Fig. 9). This relatively small value 
illustrates the substantial structural similarity 
between the two subtilisins. Deviations greater than 
1 A were found for residues 14 to 20,51 to 56, 130 to 
132, 159, 211, 239, 253 and 274 to 275. Residues 14 
to 18 (part of helix B) have a completely different 
sequence, which causes a different packing of the 
helix. Residues 51 to 56 are located in an exterior loop containing Thr55 in Novo, which is deleted in 
subtilisin Carlsberg. Residue 211 is threonine 
preceded by a eis-peptide bond in subtilisin 
Carlsberg and glycine in subtilisin Novo. All the 
other deviations were found in exterior loops. The 
C terminus Gln275 (flexible in subtilisin Novo) is 
hydrogen-bonded in subtilisin Carlsberg to a 
symmetry-equivalent enzyme molecule. The cata- 
lytic triad again shows the smallest deviations 
(<0.2 A). 
Electron density for the first seven N-terminal 
amino acid residues of Arg45-eglin could not be 
found, indicating a cleavage of this peptide by free 
subtilisin during crystallization. This observation 
was corroborated by native gel electrophoresis of 
the inhibitor isolated from crystalline material, 
which shows a slower migration towards the anode 
due to the lack of the negatively charged residues 
Glu2 and Glu6. The carbonyl oxygen atom of the 
new N terminus (Lys8) is not hydrogen-bonded to 
Va169 N as observed for wild-type eglin (Bode et al., 
1987). The electron density of Arg45-eglin (especi- 
ally in loops) is weaker than that found for subti- 
lisin, as expressed in a higher average B-value. Only 
very weak electron density was found for the side- 
chains of Glu12 and Leu27, and the loop segment 
Gly59 to Asn61, all of which are exposed to solvent. 
The structures of R45NOVO and WTCARL 
(Bode et al., 1986a) were superimposed using only 
the enzyme C” atoms. Large deviations were found 
for the orientation of the eglin cores with respect to 
their binding loops and the enzymes themselves 
with an r.m.s. deviation of 2.3 A (Fig. 9). The reac- 
tive site loop (residues Pro42 to Leu47) is nearly 
equivalent with an r.m.s. deviation of 0.32 A 
between both structures. The largest differences 
were found for C” atoms of Gly15 to Gln31 (up to 
4.33 A) and Tyr56 and Asn64 (up to 4.98 A). 
Superpositions of the cores of eglin in both 
complexes showed a rigid body motion with 
rotation angles of CI = 3.7”, /l= 1.5” and y = 11.5”. The 
r.m.s. deviation between the 56 C” atoms of the 
superimposed eglin cores was 652 A. This move- 
ment of the hydrophobic core is allowed by two 
Figure 7. Superposition of the binding loops (positions P6 to Pl’) of Arg45-eglin (open bonds) and CI-2 (filled bonds), 
both in complex with subtilisin Novo showing the accommodation of the P4 amino acid (Pro42 in Arg45-eglin; Ile56 in 
CI-2) into the S4 pocket of subtilisin Novo. Residues Pro42, and Arg45, in Arg45-eglin and TyrlO4 and Gly128 in 
subtilisin Novo are labeled. Subtilisin-Eglin Crystal Structure 361 
(a) 
(b) 
Figure 8. C”-plots of R45NOVO (open bonds, circled atoms) superimposed with that of WTCARL (filled bonds). The 
C-atoms of Arg45, in Arg45-eglin (at the bottom) and Ser221 in subtilisin Novo (at the top) are labeled. The 2 
perspectives (a) and (b) are 90” to each other. 
hinges in the vicinity of Pro42 and Leu47 (Fig. 10) 
and probably caused by different crystal contacts in 
R45NOVO and WTCARL. The main-chain torsion 
angles (4,$) of the hinge residues differ less than 
lo”, which is of the same order of magnitude as their 
accuracy. Due to the concerted motion of the core, 
hydrogen bonds making up the secondary structure 
within the core did not change significantly. The 
side-chains of Arg51 and Arg53 are still involved in 
the binding loop stabilization by forming hydrogen 
bonds with residues in the binding loop. The posi- 
tions of their guanidinium group with respect to the binding loop are very similar, although their main- 
chain atoms deviate by more than 1 A. 
Comparison of the enzyme-inhibitor interface in 
R45NOVO with that found in WTCARL revealed a 
number of differences. The number of close contacts 
( <4 A) and possible hydrogen bonds between 
inhibitor and enzyme was compared (Table 3). Only 
117 close contacts were found for the complex 
between R45NOV0, compared to 135 found in 
WTCARL. The seven possible hydrogen bonds 
between main-chain atoms were equivalent in both 
complexes. Significant differences in the interactions 
362 D. W. Heinz et al. 
R45/WT- 
Eglin I 
5, 7; Subtilisin NovoKorlsberg 
Resitie number 
Figure 9. The difference (in A) in C”-positions of 
R45NOVO and WTCARL after superposition of 274 
C”-atoms of both subtilisins using a least-squares 
procedure (r.m.s. deviation=@72 A). The maximum 
differences are labeled A (Va118), C (Tyr56), D (Serl8), F 
(Thr55), H (Serl61) and 1 (P211). The binding loop of 
Arg45-eglin (B) and the residues of the catalytic triad 
(Asp32 (E), His64 (G) and Ser221 (J)) are also labeled. with the enzyme were observed for Gly40 (P6), 
Pro42 (P4) and Arg48 (P3’). Gly40, engaged in 15 
close contacts with the subtilisin Carlsberg residues 
Gly128 to Ser130 and Tyrl04, does not substan- 
tially interact with subtilisin Novo. This is a conse- 
quence of the hinge movement of eglin in the 
proximity of Pro42, which moves Gly40 about 1.5 A 
away from the enzyme. The loss of these inter- 
actions is partly compensated by an increased 
number of interactions (20 instead of 13) of the 
P4 residue (Pro42) with the well-formed hydro- 
phobic 54 pocket (Fig. 11). In particular, five addi- 
tional contacts are found between Pro42 and 
Tyr104, which stacks on top of the pyrrolidine ring 
of Pro42. These hydrophobic interactions are almost 
as important for the reactivity of inhibitors with 
subtilisins as the Pl-Sl interactions (Powers et al., 
1977; Hirono et al., 1984). The inhibitor segment 
Pro42 to Arg45 is favorably integrated as a central 
strand in a twisted three-stranded antiparallel 
P-sheet formed with the subtilisin segments Ser125 
Table 3 
Comparison of numbers of close c&acts ( < 4 8) between subtilisin Carlsberg and wild-type eglin (first number) 
with contacts between subti&?in Novo and wild-type eglin (second number) 
P6 P5 P4 P3 P2 Pl PI’ P2’ P3’ P4 
Eglin Y35 L37 G40 S41 P42 V43 T44 L45 D46 L47 R48 Y49 R53 
Subtilisin 
Carl Now 
T33 533 
N62 N62 
G63 S63 
H64 H64 
L96 L96 
S99 D99 
GlOO GlOO 
9101 SlOl 
G102 G102 
Y104 Y104 
1107 1107 
5125 S125 
L126 L126 
G127 G127 
G128 G128 
Al29 P129 
s130 s130 
Al52 Al52 
G154 G154 
N155 N155 
F189 F189 
Y209 L209 
L217 Y217 
N218 N218 
G219 G219 
T220 T220 
s221 5221 
M222 M222 14 
9,ll l,l 
l,l 
3,2 0,l 
3,3 6,3 
1,3 32 l,l 
436 
3,O 1,6 
22 
l,l l,l 
3,3 3,3 
3,4 w-5 2,2,12* 
2,0 l,o 0,0,4* 
4,O 
W’ 
2,l 
2,2 
633 
22 
3,2 
11,9 
3,2 1,4 15,0 l,o 13,20 13,13 18,16 33,29 8,5 
O,l 
5,2 VJ 
1,4,0** 
3,3,0** 
3,3 
3,l 
3,O 
121 
3,3 4,4 O,l 
O,l 
2,3 
O,l 
13,13 7,5 14,7 0,l 4,7 l,O 
835 
O,l 
17,14 
l,l 
4,7 
12,9 
536 
436 
4,6 
2,2 
2.2 
66 
11,12 
3,O 
40 
60 
2,l 
2,2 
93 
3,l 
3,O 
l,l 
738 
2,3 
32 
13,12 
0.1 
135,117 
Significantly different contacts between subtilisin Novo and Arg45-eglin or Lys53-eglin (3rd number) are marked with * and **, 
respectively. Amino acids are represented by their l-letter codes. &ubtdisin-E&n Crystal &ructure 363 
Figure 10. Superposition of the binding loops of Arg45-eglin (in R45NOVO; open bonds) and wild-type eglin (in 
WTCARL; closed bonds) showing the hinges about which the rest of the molecule rotates in the vicinity of Pro42 and 
Leu47. Residues Gly40, Pro42, Arg45 and Leu41 are labeled. 
to Gly127 and GlylOO to Gly102, as was %lso 
observed for the complex with subtilisin Carlsberg. 
Tyr48 (P3’) no longer forms a hydrogen bond with 
Asn62 in subtilisin Novo (distance 35 A between 
Arg48 N”’ and Asn62 0”) but with Ser63 instead 
(distance 31 A between Arg48 NT2 and Ser63 Oy), 
which is glycine in subtilisin Carlsberg. 
The Sl pocket of subtilisin is a wide open hydro- 
phobic groove. Subtilisin is known for its broad 
specificity, with a distinct preference, however, for 
aromatic amino acids and leucine in position Pl 
(Markland & Smith, 1971). The structure of 
R45NOVO shows for the first time that subtilisin 
can easily accommodate the large, positively 
charged amino acid arginine. The side-chain of 
Arg45 points into the large cleft formed by subtilisin 
segments Ser125 to Pro129, Va1165 to Tyr167 and 
Ala152 to Asn155 (Fig. 12). Its extended conforma- 
tion lies nearly parallel to the stretch of Leu126 to 
Gly127. Only two possible hydrogen bonds (3.2 A) 
between the guanidinium group of Arg45 and subti- 
lisin Novo (main-chain oxygen atoms of Gly127 and 
Gly128) were found. The guanidinium group forms 
an additional five hydrogen bonds with highly cross- 
connected solvent molecules, two of which are found 
in subtilisin Carlsberg. Two solvent molecules found 
in subtilisin Carlsberg (complexed with wild-type 
eglin) are replaced by the side-chain of Arg45. The 
carboxyl group of Glu156 (Ser156 in subtilisin Carlsberg) is located in the active site cleft at a 
distance of 3.9 A to a Nq’-atom of the guanidinium 
group of Arg45. Weak electrostatic interactions 
between these groups could partly compensate for 
the positive charge of Arg45. 
The distance between the active site Ser221 0’ 
and the carbonyl carbon atom of Arg45 is 2.95 8, 
indicating a nucleophilic attack by Ser221. To see 
whether this distance, which was restrained to an 
ideal distance of 3.35 A by van der Waals’ contacts, 
was actually even shorter, the van der Waals’ 
contact restraint between the two atoms was 
removed during refinement for the last 20 cycles. 
The distance refined to 2.76 A (2.8 i% in subtilisin 
Carlsberg (Bode et al., 1987)) after cycle 97. In 
agreement with the values reported for other serine 
proteinases (Bode et al., 1987), the Xl-angle of 
Ser221 was -83”. Ser221 Oy forms a linear, favor- 
able hydrogen bond with His64 NE2 (%8 A). The 
scissile peptide bond between Arg45 and Asp46 is 
well defined in the electron density map and shows 
no distortion from planarity (o= 176”; r.m.s. devia- 
tion from the plane=@020 A), in contrast to the 
observation made by Bode et al. (19863: w= 158”) 
but in agreement with data shown by McPhalen et 
al. (1985u: o= 170”). The complex again represents 
a real intermediate in the catalytic pathway of 
subtilisin, as found in many other serine proteinase 
inhibitor complexes (Bode & Huber, 1986). 
Figure 11. Comparison of the 54 pockets in R45NOVO (open bonds) and WTCARL (filled bonds) by superposition. 
Tyr104 in subtilisin forms more hydrophobic interactions with Pro42, in R45NOVO than in WTCARL. Residues GlyM,, 
Pro42, and Arg45, in Arg45-eglin and Tyrl04 and Gly128 in subtilisin Novo are labeled. 364 D. W. Heinz et al. 
(b) 
Figure 12. Binding of Arg45 in Arg45-eglin to subtilisin Novo. (a) Arg45, and Asp46, in Arg45-eglin and Gly127 and 
Glu156 in subtilisin Novo are labeled. The positions of 3 solvent molecules surrounding Arg45, are indicated by crosses. 
Arg45, forms hydrogen bonds with these solvent molecules and the carbonyl oxygen atom of Gly127. (b) Part of a 
2F, - F, map showing electron density (contour level = 251~) for this region. 
(g) Structure of Lys53-eglin 
The vicinity of Lys53 in Lys53-eglin was 
compared with that of Arg53 in wild-type eglin. The 
guanidinium group of Arg53 in wild-type eglin is 
involved in several interactions with residues 
belonging to both eglin and subtilisin as well as with 
some solvent molecules (Fig. 13). The NV’ atom 
forms hydrogen bonds with the carbonyl oxygen of 
Thr44 (P2) and two solvent molecules located 
between the core and binding loop; the N’J2 atom 
with the side-chain oxygen of Thr44 (PZ), the 
carbonyl oxygen of Asp99 in subtilisin and two 
solvent molecules located in the enzyme-inhibitor 
interface. The side-chain of Lys53 is not as well 
defined as Arg53, indicating greater flexibility. The 
conformation from Cd onward deviates strongly 
from that found for Arg53 (Fig. 13). The side-chain 
points into the space between the binding loop and 
the core of eglin. The positively charged NC-atom 
occupies the position of a solvent molecule found in 
wild-type eglin. It forms only a single hydrogen bond to a solvent molecule (0393, also found in 
wild-type eglin), which itself interacts with the 
carbonyl oxygen atoms of Thr44 (P2) and Asp46 
(Pl’). As a result, Lys53 no longer interacts with the 
binding loop directly, but instead through a 
bridging solvent molecule. The former position of 
the guanidinium group of Arg53 is now occupied by 
a new solvent molecule (0337), which forms hydro- 
gen bonds with the carbonyl oxygen of Asp99 in 
subtilisin: the NV1 atom of Arg51 in the inhibitor 
and a solvent molecule in the enzyme-inhibitor 
interface. 
The side-chain atoms of Lys53 have much higher 
temperature factors than those of Arg53 in wild- 
type eglin. The B-values steadily increase along the 
side-chain from 23 A2 for C? to 78 A2 for NC, 
compared to 15 A2 for the guanidinium group of 
Arg53 in wild-type eglin. The position of the Lys53 
side-chain was determined by inspecting an FO - Fc 
Fourier map with structure factors calculated from 
co-ordinates where the atoms in question (Cy to Nr 
in Lys53 and 0337) had been omitted (Fig. 14). 
Subtilisin-Eglin Crystal Structure 365 
Figure 13. Superposition of LysBl-eglin (open bonds with circled atoms) and wild-type eglin (filled bonds), both Figure 13. Superposition of LysBl-eglin (open bonds with circled atoms) and wild-type eglin (filled bonds), both 
complexed with subtilisin Novo. Leu45, Thr44, Arg51 and Lys53 in Lys53-eglin, Asp99 in subtilisin Novo and the complexed with subtilisin Novo. Leu45, Thr44, Arg51 and Lys53 in Lys53-eglin, Asp99 in subtilisin Novo and the 
solvent molecules 0393 and 0337 are labeled. The position of 0393 in Lys53-eglin is also occupied by a solvent molecule solvent molecules 0393 and 0337 are labeled. The position of 0393 in Lys53-eglin is also occupied by a solvent molecule 
in wild-type eglin (cross). The position of the side-chain of Lys53 deviates from that of Arg53 in wild-type eglin. in wild-type eglin (cross). The position of the side-chain of Lys53 deviates from that of Arg53 in wild-type eglin. 
The distance of the hydroxyl group of Ser221 to 
the carbonyl atoms of the scissile bond residue 
Leu45 is 2.1 A, but when left unrestrained during 
refinement, a further shortening to 1.9 A was 
observed. The torsion angle x1 of Ser221 is -31”. 
The electron density map shows continuous but not 
well-resolved density between Ser221 Oy and the 
carbonyl carbon of Leu45. The distance of Ser221 Oy 
to His64 N” is 2.9 A. These observations, although 
at this resolution not decisive, might indicate a 
more progressed nucleophilic attack of Ser221 when 
compared to wild-type or Arg45-eglin. The scissile 
peptide bond, however, shows no deviation from 
planarity (o= 175”). It has to be kept in mind that 
data only to 2.4 A do not allow complete resolution 
of individual atoms. (h) Model structure of the complex between 
Arg45-eglin and bovine trypsin 
Eglin was converted from an elastase to a trypsin 
inhibitor by the single point mutation Leu45-+Arg 
in position Pl. The inhibitory potency of 
Arg45-eglin for trypsin (Ki= 10-l ’ M) is as strong as 
that found in many naturally occurring trypsin 
inhibitors. To find a structural explanation for this 
new property, the crystal structure of Arg45-eglin 
(in complex with subtilisin Novo) was compared 
with the crystal structure of basic pancreatic 
trypsin inhibitor (BPTI, in complex with trypsin), 
the strongest trypsin inhibitor known (Ki = lo- l4 M; 
Lazdunski et al., 1974). These inhibitors are similar 
in size but non-homologous in their amino acid 
Figure 14. Part of an F, - F, omit map showing electron density only for the atoms that were omitted (Cy to NC of 
Lys53 and 0337) prior to structure factor calculation. 366 D. W. Heinz et al. 
Figure 15. Superposition of Arg45-eglin (C’ atoms, open bonds) with BPTI ((Y-atoms and all atoms in position P3 to 
P3’, filled bonds), which was carried out only for residues in position P3 to P3’ of both molecules. 
sequence. The polypeptide backbone of the residues 
in positions P3 to P3’ of Arg45-eglin (Va143, Thr44, 
Arg45, Asp46, Leu47 and Arg48) and BPTI (Prol3, 
Cysl4, Lysl5, Ala16, Argl7 and Ile18) were super- 
imposed using the co-ordinates of the complex 
between BPTI and trypsin refined at 1.9 A resolu- 
tion (Huber et al., 1974), taken from the Protein 
Data Bank (Bernstein et al., 1977). The backbones 
of the binding loops from position P3 to P3’ were 
very similar with an r.m.s. deviation for the main- 
chain atoms of @48 i% (Fig. 15). The rest of both 
inhibitors have no structural similarity. When 
superimposing Arg45-eglin and BPTI in the 
BPTI-trypsin structure, the side-chain of 
Arg45-eglin can be fitted into the active site cleft of 
trypsin, in which the guanidinium group of Arg45 
could form a salt bridge with the carboxylic group 
of Asp189 at the bottom of the active site cleft of 
trypsin. Unfavorable contacts between both mole- 
cules in the model complex were observed in only 
two regions. Pro42 in Arg45-eglin makes close 
contacts ( < 2 A) with Gly216 and Ser217 in trypsin, 
which are located in a /?-strand that strongly inter- 
acts with residues P3 to Pl under formation of a 
/?-sheet. Likewise, atoms of Tyr49 in Arg45-eglin are 
located too close (< 2 8) to Tyr39 in trypsin. Both 
unfavorable contacts are presumably not present in 
the real complex due to the flexibility of the amino 
acid side-chains involved. All hydrogen bonds found 
between BPTI and trypsin (in the real structure) 
are found also between Arg45-eglin and trypsin (in 
the model structure). The interface between 
Arg45-eglin and trypsin is restricted to amino acid 
residues in positions P3 to P3’ and the corre- 
sponding subsites in the enzyme with the PI-S1 
interaction predominating. Pro42 (P4) and Tyr49 
(P4’) might form hydrophobic interactions with 
side-chains of trypsin, although there are no distinct 
S4 or 54’ subsites in the enzyme. Due to the lack of a secondary binding loop as found in BPTI, and the 
wedge-shaped structure of Arg45-eglin, no addi- 
tionaJ interactions between Arg45-eglin and trypsin 
are expected. Based on these observations and 
experimental kinetic data, it is evident that only a 
small number of specific interactions between 
trypsin and Arg45-eglin is sufficient to reach a 
strong inhibition (Ki= 10-l’ M for Arg45-eglin). 
More intimate interactions, however, as found in the 
complex BPTI/trypsin, may be responsible for an 
increase in the inhibitory potency (Ki= IO-l4 M) 
and specificity. 
4. Discussion 
(a) Structural mobility in eglin 
Eglin can be divided into two parts; the reactive 
site binding loop and the hydrophobic core. The 
hydrophobic core of eglin shows significant differ- 
ences in its position relative to the reactive site 
binding loop, depending on the crystal form of the 
eglin-subtilisin complex. A rigid body rotation that 
hinges around Pro42 and Leu47 leads to shifts of the 
core of up to 5 i% for C’-atoms, when comparing 
both inhibitors in WTNOVO and WTCARL. The 
conformations of the binding loops (positions P3 to 
P3’), however, remain nearly identical due to their 
contacts with the enzyme. The positions of the 
guanidinium groups of Arg51 and Arg53 with 
respect to the binding loop are also very similar, 
although their main-chain atoms deviate by more 
than 1 A, indicating maintenance of the binding 
loop stabilization. Analysis of the packing of the 
molecules in WTNOVO and WTCARL showed that 
the difference in crystal form leading to positional 
differences of the eglin core is caused almost exclu- 
sively by those amino acids different in the subtili- 
sins. This suggests that only a few amino acid Subtiliain-Eglin Crystal Structure 367 
F 
the] rmitase crystal form I (blue) and thermitase crystal form II (green) by using only main-chain atoms of residues in 
IJO. ition P3 to P2’. (a) Onlv Ca-atoms. (b) All atoms. The positions of the N terminus (LysS), the C terminus (Gly70) and 
the Pl residue Leu& are labeled. ‘igure 16. Superposition of 4 eglin molecules from complexes with subtilisin Nova (yellow), subtilisin Carlsberg (red), 
replacements at the surface of a protein can affect 
crystallographic packing, which subsequently can 
affect the structure. 
A similar rigid body motion of the core of eglin 
has been reported for the complex between thermi- 
tase and eglin, which crystallized in two different 
space groups (Dauter et d., 1988; Gros et al., 1989). 
The core of eglin in crystal form I could be rotated 
as a rigid body by 194” with respect to that found 
in crystal form II around a rotation axis running 
through Ser41 and Leu47. These findings demon- 
strate that there is considerable flexibility between 
the reactive site binding loop and the core in solu- 
tion, and that only one of many possible conforma- 
tions of the core is found “frozen” in the respective 
crystal, depending on intermolecular contacts in the 
crystals. Eglin molecules, co-crystallized with the serine 
proteinases subtilisin Novo, subtilisin Carlsberg and 
thermitase in four different space groups, were 
superimposed using a global least-squares super- 
position of structurally equivalent C”-atoms of the 
enzymes. The co-ordinates of eglin in complex with 
the following enzymes were used: subtilisin Novo 
(space group P3121, this work), subtilisin Carlsberg 
(space group Pl, Bode et al., 1986a), thermitase 
(crystal form I: space group P2r2,2,, Dauter et al., 
1988) and thermitase (crystal form II: space group 
P2,2,2,, with different packing and cell edges 
compared to crystal form I, Gros et al., 1989). In 
every complex, the eglin cores show a different 
orientation due to a rigid body rotation that hinges 
around Pro42 and Leu47 (Fig. 16). The largest 
deviations were found for residue Gly59, which 
368 D. W. Heinz et al. 
deviates by 55 A in the eglin complexes with both 
subtilisins. 
In contrast, the very rigid molecule BPTI, which 
is a strong and highly specific trypsin inhibitor, 
shows no significant differences between its free and 
complexed crystal structure (Huber & Bode, 1978). 
Due to the absence of disulfide bridges, however, the 
framework of eglin is not rigid enough to resist 
changes induced by crystal packing. 
The flexibility of the eglin binding loop has been 
shown by nuclear magnetic resonance studies of free 
eglin in solution (Hyberts $ Wagner, 1996). 
H-exchange rates of eglin for the binding loop 
(Ser41 to Leu47) imply a different conformation 
when compared with that found in the crystal struc- 
ture of complexed eglin. In addition, the hydrogen 
bonding network in the solution structure is not as 
pronounced as in the crystal structure. This implies 
that the position of the binding loop relative to the 
core of eglin is rather pliant, becoming fixed only 
upon complex formation with its target enzyme. 
This clearly broadens the inhibitory specificity of 
eglin towards serine proteinases, as suggested by 
Read & James (1986). The partly flexible reactive 
site, which is not fixed by disulfide bridges, can 
adapt to slightly different active sites. 
(b) Eglin-&t&sin Novo interface 
Despite the high degree of structural similarity 
between subtilisins Novo and Carlsberg, a number 
of differences were found when comparing the inter- 
faces of both enzymes with eglin. The number of 
close contacts between subtilisin Novo and eglin is 
significantly fewer than in WTCARL. This is mainly 
because the area of the interface, which extends 
from position P6 to P3’ in WTCARL, is shorter in 
WTNOVO. No interaction with subtilisin Novo 
closer than 4 A is found for Gly40 (P6) or Ser41 
(P5). Instead, the hydrophobic interactions between 
Pro42 (P4) and the 54 pocket are stronger. This 
may compensate for the loss of interactions between 
S&P5 and S6P6. In particular, more hydrophobic 
interactions are found in WTNOVO between Pro42 
(P4) and Tyr104, which stacks nicely on top of the 
pyrollidinium ring of Pro42. A similar observation 
was made by Gros et al. (1989) for the interactions of 
Pro42 in eglin with thermitase (mainly with Trpl12, 
which corresponds to Tyr104 in subtilisin). Fewer 
interactions were found between Arg48 (P3’) and 
Asn62 of subtilisin Novo, which is again caused by 
the hinged rigid body motion in eglin. 
Due to the absence of any information about the 
structure of WTNOVO in solution, it is not possible 
to determine whether the changed interactions are 
present in solution or simply caused by the different 
crystal packing of the complexes (crystallographic 
artefact), which leads to the rigid body motion in 
eglin. 
(c) Inhibitory specifiity of eglin 
The single point mutation Leu45-+Arg in position 
Pl of eglin was sufficient to change it from an elastase to a trypsin inhibitor. The comparison of 
the crystal structures of Arg45-eglin and BPTT 
could explain this specificity change. In the model 
structure of Arg45-eglin and trypsin, the inhibitor 
forms interactions with the enzyme mainly via 
amino acid residues located in the positions P3 to 
P3’, especially between the Pl residue and the Sl 
subsite. 
In subtilisin Novo, however, the guanidinium 
group of Arg45 does not bind specifically to a nega- 
tively charged residue in the active site of subtilisin, 
but rather unspecifically to the main-chain oxygen 
atom of Gly127 and a number of solvent molecules 
in subtilisin Novo. There is no compensation of the 
positive charge of Arg45. Only weak electrostatic 
interactions between Glu156, located in the active 
site pocket of subtilisin, and Arg45 (distance 3.9 A) 
seem possible. That this interaction is minor is 
indicated by the fact that subtilisin Carlsberg, 
which carries a serine residue at position 156, is 
inhibited by Arg45-eglin by the same order of 
magnitude as subtilisin Novo. 
Arg45-eglin does not inhibit human thrombin or 
porcine pancreatic kallikrein, despite their prefer- 
ence for basic amino acids in position Pl. This can 
be explained by attempting to fit eglin to the crystal 
structures of both enzymes. The structure of 
thrombin (Bode et al., 1989) shows a narrow active 
site cleft restricted by two tryptophan residues in 
extended loops. These loops probably prevent the 
access of the extended binding loop of eglin. In 
kallikrein (Bode et al., 1983), some characteristic 
loops, which shield the active site cleft, reduce the 
accessibility of the eglin binding loop. These 
examples show that not only the Pl amino acid 
determines the specificity of an inhibitor towards 
serine proteinases, but so does the exact comple- 
mentarity of the binding loop and the active site of 
the enzyme. 
(d) Binding loop stabilization in eglin 
The hydrogen bonds formed between Arg53 and 
Thr44 in wild-type eglin participate in a hydrogen 
bonding network that stabilizes the conformation of 
the reactive site binding loop. The rapid association 
of eglin with, for example, elastase (Ic,,= 
IO’ M-I s-l) is promoted by the reactive site 
binding loop of eglin being held in a rigid conforma- 
tion highly complementary to the enzyme. The 
binding loop of eglin is stabilized by extensive 
hydrogen bonding with its core. Besides tight 
binding, a low hydrolytic constant (Khyd) is a neces- 
sity for good inhibition. This equilibrium constant is 
between the native (intact) and the modified 
(cleaved) inhibitor and is usually close to unity for 
good inhibitors (Laskowski & Kato, 1980). The 
barriers to release of the cleaved inhibitor after 
hydrolysis from the enzyme are provided by the 
hydrogen bonding network, which reduces the 
conformational freedom of a cleaved inhibitor. This 
is analogous to a binding loop stabilized by disulfide 
bridges, as in BPTI (Huber et al., 1974) and the Subtilisin-Eglin Crystal Structure 369 
third domains of the ovomucoid inhibitors (Bode et 
al., 1985). 
The inhibitory activity for subtilisin and elastase 
was essentially maintained in Lys53-eglin. Once 
cleaved, however, Lys53-eglin dissociates more 
rapidly from subtilisin. A similar observation was 
made for the inhibitor CT-l, a close relative of CI-2, 
which has Phe in place of Arg61, the equivalent 
residue to Arg53 in eglin (Svendsen et al., 1982). The 
structure of Lys53-eglin made possible analysis of 
the structural effect of the replacement Arg53+Lys 
in detail. The side-chain of Lys53 is weakly defined 
in the structure indicating high flexibility. The 
NC-atom can no longer form hydrogen bonds with 
Thr44 located in the binding loop. Instead, it inter- 
acts with a solvent molecule (0393), which itself 
forms a hydrogen bond to the main-chain oxygen 
atom of Thr44. These structural changes lead to a 
weakening of the binding loop stabilization, 
followed by an accelerated cleavage of the scissile 
bond. This proposal is corroborated by the kinetic 
data. 
The hydrogen bond formed between the guanidi- 
nium group of Arg53 in wild-type eglin and the 
main-chain oxygen atom of Asp99 in subtilisin 
Novo is not present in Lys53-eglin. Instead, the 
former space of the guanidinium group is occupied 
by a solvent molecule (0337). 
The distance of Ser221 Oy to the Pl main-chain 
carbonyl carbon atom is about 2 A, significantly 
shorter when compared with other proteinase 
inhibitor complexes (2.3 to 2.8 A: Read & James, 
1986), possibly indicating a further progressed 
nucleophilic attack by Ser221. Higher-resolution 
analysis using synchrotron radiation for crystals of 
K53NOVO should lead to a better model, allowing 
more reliable answers to the points discussed above. 
Further eglin mutants in this area are under investi- 
gation to augment our understanding of the non- 
covalent binding loop stabilization in eglin. 
Mutagenic oligonucleotides were synthesized and 
purified by H. Rink, Ciba-Geigy, Basel, which is grate- 
fully acknowledged. The plasmid pML147 used for the 
expression of recombinant eglin was a kind gift from Dr 
M. Liersch, Ciba-Geigy, Baael. Many thanks to him and 
Dr B. Chaudhuri, Ciba-Geigy, Base1 for their help in 
doing site-directed mutagenesis. We thank Professor J. N. 
Jansonius (Biocenter, BaYel), who was kind enough to 
make available equipment for data collection and 
processing. We thank Dr P. Gros (University of 
Groningen, The Netherlands) for providing the co-ordi- 
nates of the complexes between thermitrtse and eglin. The 
critical reading of the manuscript by Dr J. van Oostrum 
and L. Chow is gratefully acknowledged. The work 
described here formed part of the Ph.D. thesis of D.W.H. 
References 
Bernstein, F. C., Koetzle, T. F., Williams, G. J. B., Meyer, 
E. F., Brice, M. D., Rodgers, J. R., Kennard, O., 
Shimanouchi, T. & Tasumi, M. (1977). The Protein 
Data Bank: A Computer-based Archival File for 
Macromolecular Structures. J. Mol. Biol. 112. 
535-542. Bode, W. & Huber, R. (1986). Crystal Structures of 
Pancreatic Serine Endopeptidases. In Molecular and 
Cellular Basis of Dige&ion (Desnuelle, P., Sjostrom, 
H. $ Noren, O., eds), pp. 213-234, Elsevier, 
Amsterdam. 
Bode, W., Chen, Z., Bert&, K., Kutzbach, C., 
Schmidt-Kastner, G. & Bartunik, H. (1983). Refined 
2 A X-ray Crystal Structure of Porcine Pancreatic 
Kallikrein A, a Specific Trypsin-like Serine 
Proteinase., J. Mol. Biol. 164, 237-282. 
Bode, W., Epp, E., Huber, R., Laskowski, M., Jr & 
Ardelt, W. (1985). The Crystal and Molecular 
Structure of the Third Domain of Silver Pheasant 
Ovomucoid (OMSVP3). Eur. J. Biochem. 147, 
387-395. 
Bode, W., Papamokos, E., Musil, D., Seemiiller, U. & 
Fritz, H. (1986a). Refined 1.2 w Crystal Structure of 
the Complex Formed between Subtilisin Carlsberg 
and the Inhibitor Eglin c. EMBO J. 5, 813-818. 
Bode, W., Wei, A.-Z., Huber, R., Meyer, E., Travis, J. & 
Neumann, S. (1986b). X-ray Crystal Structure of the 
Complex of Human Leukocyte Elastase (PMN 
Elastase) and the Third Domain of the Turkey 
Ovomucoid Inhibitor. EMBO J. 5, 2453-2458. 
Bode, W., Papamokos, E. 6 Musil, D. (1987). The 
High-resolution X-ray Crystal Structure of the 
Complex Formed between Subtilisin Carlsberg and 
Eglin c, an Elastase Inhibitor from the Leech Hirudo 
medicinalis. Eur. J. B&hem. 166, 673492. 
Bode, W., Mayr, I., Baumann, U., Huber, R., Stone, S. R. 
& Hofsteenge, J. (1989). The Refined 1.9 A Crystal 
Structure of Human a-Thrombin: Interaction with D- 
Phe-Pro-Arg Chloromethylketone and Significance of 
the Tyr-Pro-Pro-Trp Insertion Segment. EMBO J. 8, 
3467-3475. 
Braun, N. J., Bodmer, J. L., Virca, G. D., Metz-Virca, G., 
Maschler, R., Bieth, J. G. & Schnebli, H.-P. (1987). 
Kinetic Studies on the Interaction of Eglin c with 
Human Leukocyte Elastase and Cathepsin G. Biol. 
Chem. Hoppe-Seyler, 368, 29%308. 
Clarke, L. 6 Carbon, J. (1978). Functional Expression of 
Cloned Yeast DNA in Escherichia coli: Specific 
Complementation of Argininosuccinate Lyase (argH) 
Mutation. J. Mol. Biol. 120, 517-532. 
Crowther, R. A. & Blow, D. M. (1967). A Method of 
Positioning a Known Molecule in an Unknown 
Crystal Structure. Acta Crystallogr. 23, 544-548. 
Dauter, Z., Betzel, C., HGhne, W. E., Ingelman, M. & 
Wilson, K. S. (1988). Crystal Structure of a Complex 
between Thermitase from Thermoactinomyces vulgaris 
and the Leech Inhibitor Eglin. FEBS Letters, 236, 
171-178. 
Davies, D. R. & Segal, D. M. (1971). Protein 
Crystallization: Microtechniques Involving Vapor 
Diffusion. Methods Enzymol. 22, 266-269. 
Deisenhofer, J. & Steigemann, W. (1974). The Model of 
the Basic Pancreatic Trypsin Inhibitor Refined at 
1.5 A Resolution. In Proteinase Inhibitors, Bayer 
Symposium 5 (Fritz, H., Tschesche, H., Greene, L. J. 
& Truscheit, E., eds), pp. 484-496, Springer, Berlin. 
Drenth, J., Hol, W. G. J., Jansonius, J. N. & Koekoek, R. 
(1972). Subtilisin Novo. The Three-Dimensional 
Structure and Its Comparison with Subtilisin BPN’. 
Eur. J. Biochem. 26, 177-181. 
Fox, G. C. & Holmes, K. C. (1966). An Alternative 
Method of Solving the Layer Scaling Equations of 
Hamilton, Rollett and Sparks. Acta Crystallogr. 20, 
886-891. 
French, S. & Wilson, K. (1978). On the Treatment of 370 D. W. Heinz et al. 
Negative Intensity Observations. Acta Crystal&w. 
sect. A, 34, 517-525. and CI-2-Subtilisin Novo. Biochemistry, 27, 
6582-6598. 
Gros, P., Betzel, C., Dauter, Z., Wilson, K. S. & Hol, 
W. G. J. (1989). Molecular Dynamics Refinement of a 
Thermitase-Eglin c Complex at 198 A Resolution 
and a Comparison of Two Crystal Forms that Differ 
in Calcium Content. J. Mol. Biol. 210, 347-367. 
Griitter, M. G., Miirki, W. & Walliser, H.-P. (1985). 
Crystals of the Complex between Recombinant 
N-Acetyleglin c and Subtilisin. J. Biol. Chem. 260, 
1143611437. McPhalen, C. A., Schnebli, H. P. & James, M. N. G. 
(1985u). Crystal and Molecular Structure of the 
Inhibitor Eglin from Leeches in Complex with 
Subtilisin Carlsberg. FEBS Letters, 188, 55-58. 
McPhalen, C. A., Svendsen, I., Jonassen, I. & James, 
M. N. G. (19856). Crystal and Molecular Structure of 
the Inhibitor CI-2 from Barley Seeds in Complex 
with Subtilisin Novo. Proc. Nat. Acad. Sci., U.S.A. 
82, 7242-7246. 
Heinz, D. W. (1999). Structural and Functional Studies of 
Mutants of the Serine Proteinase Inhibitor Eglin c. 
Ph.D. thesis, University of Base], Switzerland. 
Hendrickson, W. A. $ Konnert, J. H. (1989). 
Stereochemically Restrained Crystallographic 
Least-Squares Refinement of Macromolecular 
Structures. In Bknrwlecular Structure, Function, 
Conformation and Evolution (Srinivisan, R., ed.), 
vol. 1, pp. 43-57, Pergamon, Oxford. 
Hirono, S., Akagawa, H., Mitsui, Y. & Iitaka, Y. (1984). 
Crystal Structure at 26 A Resolution of the Complex 
of Subtilisin BPN’ with Streptomyces subtilisin 
Inhibitor. J. Mol. Biol. 178, 389413. 
Huber, R. BE Bode, W. (1978). Structural Basis of the 
Activation and Action of Trypsin. Act. Chem. Res. 
11, 114-122. Messerschmidt, A. & Pflugrath, J. W. (1987). Crystal 
Orientation and X-ray Pattern Prediction Routines 
for Area-detector Diffractometer Systems in 
Macromolecular Crystallography. J. APP~. 
Crystallogr. 20, 306-315. 
North, A. C. T., Phillips, D. C. & Mathews, F. S. (1968). 
A Semi-empirical Method of Absorption Correction. 
Acta Crystullogr. sect. A, 24, 351-359. 
Nyborg, J. & Wonacott, A. J. (1977). Computer 
Programs. In The Rotation Method in Crystallography 
(Arndt, U. W. & Wonacott, A. J., eds), pp. 139152, 
North-Holland, New York. 
Powers, J. C., Lively, M. 0. & Tippett, J. T. (1977). 
Inhibition of Subtilisin BPN’ with Peptide 
Chloromethyl Ketones. Biochim. Biophys. Acta, 480, 
246261. 
Huber, R., Kukla, D., Bode, W., Schwager, P., Bartels, 
K., Deisenhofer, J. & Steigemann, W. (1974). 
Structure of the Complex Formed by Bovine Trypsin 
and Bovine Pancreatic Trypsin Inhibitor. II. 
Crystallographic Refinement at 1.9 A Resolution. 
J. Mol. Biol. 89, 73-101. 
Hyberts, S. G. & Wagner, G. (1996). Sequence-specific ‘H 
NMR Assignments and Secondary Structure of 
Eglin c. Biochemistry, 29, 14651474. 
Jonassen, I. & Svendsen, I. (1982). Identification of the 
Reactive Sites in Two Homologous Serine Proteinase 
Inhibitors Isolated from Barley. Carlsberg Res. 
Commun. 47, 199203. Ramakrishnan, C. & Ramachandran, G. N. (1965). 
Stereochemical Criteria for Polypeptide and Protein 
Chain Conformations. II. Allowed Conformations for 
a Pair of Peptide Units. Biophys. J. 5, 909-933. 
Raschdorf, F., Dahinden, R., Domon, B., Miiller, D. $ 
Richter, W. J. (1986). MS Analysis of Large Peptides 
Synthesised by Recombinant DNA Technology. 
Application of FAB/MSMS and ThermospraylMSMS 
in the Structural Characterisation of Recombinant 
Eglin c. In Mass Spectrometry in the Analysis of Large 
Molecules (McNeal, C. J., ed.), pp. 49-65, Wiley, 
Chichester, UK. 
Jones, T. A. (1978). A Graphics Model Building and 
Refinement System for Macromolecules. J. Appl. 
Crystallcgr. 11, 268-272. 
Kabsch, W. (1988). Automatic Indexing of Rotation 
Diffraction Patterns. J. Appl. Crystallogr. 21, 67-71. 
Laskowski, M. & Kato, I. (1989). Protein Inhibitors of 
Proteinases. Annu. Rev. Biochem. 49, 593-626. 
Lazdunski, M., Vincent, J.-P., Schweitz, H., 
Peron-Renner, M. t Pudles, J. (1974). The 
Mechanism of Association of Trypsin (or 
Chymotrypsin) with the Pancreatic Trypsin 
Inhibitors (Kunitz and Kazal). Kinetics and 
Thermodynamics of the Interaction. In Proteinase 
Inhibitors, Bayer Symposium 5 (Fritz, H., Tschesche, 
H., Greene, L. J. & Truscheit, E., eds), pp. 426431, 
Springer, Berlin. Read, R. J. (1986). Improved Fourier Coefficients for 
Maps Using Phases from Partial Structures with 
Errors. Acta Crystullogr. sect. A, 42, 146-149. 
Read, R. J. & James, M. N. G. (1986). Introduction to the 
Protein Inhibitors. In Proteinu-se Inhibitors (Barrett, 
A. J. & Salvesen, G., eds), pp. 301-336, Elsevier, 
Amsterdam. 
Richardson, M. & Cossins, L. (1974). Chymotryptic 
Inhibitor I from Potatoes: The Amino Acid 
Sequences of Subunits B, C and D. FEBS Letters, 45, 
11-13. 
Rink, H., Liersch, M., Sieber, P. & Meyer, F. (1984). 
A Large Fragment Approach to DNA Synthesis: 
Total Synthesis of a Gene for the Protease Inhibitor 
Eglin c from the Leech Hirudo medicinalis. Nucl. 
Acids Res. 12, 6364-6387. 
Maier, K., Miiller, H., Tesch, R., Trolp, R., Witt, I. & 
Holzer, H. (1979). Primary Structure of Yeast 
Proteinase B Inhibitor 2. J. Biol. Chem. 254, 
1255512561. 
Markland, F. S., Jr t Smith, E. L. (1971). Subtilisins: 
Primary Structure, Chemical and Physical 
Properties. In The Enzymes (Boyer, P. D., ed.), 
pp. 561-608, Academic Press, New York. 
Matthews, B. W. (1968). Solvent Content of Protein 
Crystals. J. Mol. Biol. 33, 491497. 
McPhalen, C. A. & James, M. N. G. (1988). Structural 
Comparison of Two Serine Proteinase-Protein 
Inhibitor Complexes: Eglin-c-Subtilisin Carlsberg Rossmann, M. G. (1979). Processing Oscillation 
Diffraction Data for Very Large Unit Cells with an 
Automatic Convolution Technique and Profile 
Fitting. J. Appl. Crystallogr. 12, 225-238. 
Russell, A. J. & Fersht, A. R. (1986). Commercial Samples 
of Subtilisin BPN’. Nature (London), 321, 733. 
Schechter, I. & Berger, A. (1967). On the Size of the 
Active Site in Proteases. I. Papain. B&hem. 
Biophys. Res. Commun. 27, 157-162. 
Schnebli, H. P. & Braun, N. J. (1986). Protein&se 
Inhibitors as Drugs. In Proteinase Inhibitors (Barrett, 
A. J. & Salvesen, G., eds), pp. 613-627, Elsevier, 
Amsterdam. 
Seemiiller, U., Meier, M., Ohlsson, K., Miiller, H.-P. & Subtilisin-Eglin Crystal Structure 371 
Fritz, H. (1977). Isolation and Characterization of a 
Low Molecular Weight Inhibitor (of Chymotrypsin 
and Human Granulocytic Elastase and Cathepsin G) 
from Leeches. Hoppe-Seyler’a Z. Physiol. Chem. 358, 
1105-1117. 
Seemiiller, U., Eulitz, M., Fritz, H. & Strobl, A. (1980). 
Structure of the Elaetaae-cathepsin G Inhibitor of the 
Leech Hirwlo medicinalis. Hoppe-Seyler’s Z. Physiol. 
Chem. 361, 1841-1846. 
Sim, G. A. (1960). A Note on the Heavy Atom Method. 
A& Crystullogr. 13, 511-512. 
Stryer, L., Kendrew, J. C. & Watson, H. C. (1964). The 
Mode of Attachment of the Azide Ion to Sperm 
Whale Metmyoglobin. J. Mol. Biol. 8, 96-104. 
Sussman, J. L., Holbrook, S. R., Church, G. M. & Kim, 
S.-H. (1977). A Structure-factor Least Squares 
Refinement Procedure for Macromolecular Structures 
using Constrained and Restrained Parameters. Acta 
Cystallogr. sect. A, 33, 80&804. 
Svendsen, I., Boisen, S. & Hejgaard, J. (1982). Amino Acid Sequence of Serine Protease Inhibitor CI-1 from 
Barley, Homology with Barley Inhibitor CI-2, 
Potato Inhibitor 1 and Leech Eglin. Carlsberg Res. 
Commun. 47, 45-53. 
Welker, N. E. & Campbell, L. L. (1967). Unrelatedness of 
Bacillus amyloliquefaciens and Bacillus subtilis. 
J. Bacterial. 94, 11241130. 
Wilson, K. S., Stura, E. A., Wild, D. L., Todd, R. J., 
Stuart, D. I., Babu, Y. S., Jenkins, J. A., Standing, 
T. S., Johnson, L. N., Fourme, R., Kahn, R., 
Gadet, A., Bartels, K. S. & Bartunik, H. D. (1983). 
Macromolecular Crystallography with Synchrotron 
Radiation. II. Results. J. Appl. Crystallogr. 16, 
2841. 
Wright, C. S., Alden, R. A. & Kraut, J. (1969). Structure 
of Subtilisin BPN’ at 2.5 A Resolution. Nature 
(London), 221, 235-242. 
Zoller, M. J. & Smith, M. (1983). Oligonucleotide-directed 
Mutagenesis of DNA Fragments Cloned into Ml3 
Vectors. Methods Enzynwl. 199, 468-500. 
Edited by R. Huber 